Dances and Recreation Files, 1881-[ongoing]
Smith College Archives
Dances and Recreation Files
1881-[ongoing]
Smith College.
RG 80 UUID:af2599df-1b25-4ec0-9205-d1d5f57463c4
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
The files contain mostly photographs, dance cards and invitations. Some photographs can tell their own story such as with the "Superdance USA" of 1981, with its succession of 4 photographs. Information about the Supper Dance can be derived from the many press releases about the event.
The tradition of dances and recreation at Smith is longstanding. From social gatherings, teas, and parties in the 1880s and 1890s, to the hosting of "Supper Dance" Weekend from the 1920s through the 1940s, to the present day traditions of Friday Teas, Winter Weekend, Spring Weekend and Rugby Prom, Smith has seen its fair share of parties.
While much of the information regarding the gatherings cannot be found in the folders, many of the photographs tell their own stories.
There is a plethora of information about the Supper Dance. Preceded by 'walk arounds" in the 1880s, when the Glee Club was founded in 1888, it hosted a yearly spring concert, which gradually evolved into Spring Dance and Supper Dance. Organized by a student committee, the dance was open to the entire college, with each house hosting its own dance and hired bands. Because Smith women are "unusually smart as well as unusually attractive, and... their hospitality is rightly famous" according to an article for LIFE magazine, the Supper dance was unusually popular and especially well anticipated by male guests. As their hosts, Smithies paid for their weekend and were allowed to cut in on couples and choose their dance partners. The weekend consisted of Friday classes, dancing lasting the greater part of Saturday with a break for dinner, and Sunday activities. The dance was so famous as to attract photographer Alfred Eisenstaedt of LIFE magazine to take pictures for an article about the Supper Dance in 1937. The Supper Dance continued until the 1940s, probably when wartime took its toll.
Information found in the files is incomplete and contains mostly photographs, dance cards and invitations.
Photographs can sometimes tell their own story such as with the "Superdance USA" of 1981, with its succession of 4 photographs. However, many photographs are vague and do not communicate who, when, where or why. Present day dances and recreations are unaccounted for.
Information about the Supper Dance can be derived from the many press releases about the event.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The files are open to public research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
History of the Collection
The Smith College Archives collected the files on Dances and Recreation over time.
Search Terms
Smith College--History--Sources.; Smith College--Students--Social life and customs.; Ballroom dancing--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Afternoon teas--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Recreation--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Women college students--Massachusetts--Northampton--Social life and customs.
Additional Information
Related Material
Related Materials include other social events, such as Class Suppers, Junior and Senior Proms, are documented in the specific class records found in 80. Students/Class Records. A listing of this material is available at the Smith College Archives.
- Card Parties 1887-1917 (Box 1)
- Dance Cards/Invitations 1884-1889 (Box 1)
- Dances, General Photographs 1979-1982, undated (Box 1)
- Dress Parties 1882, undated (Box 1)
- Faculty Teas 1894-1916 (Box 1)
- "German" 1882-1889 (Box 1)
- Group Dances 1894-1938 (Box 1)
- House Dances 1894-1979 (Box 1)
- House Dances Photographs undated (Box 1)
- Mixers 1960-1964 (Box 1)
- Parties 1986-87, 1990 (Box 1)
- Picnics undated (Box 1)
- Receptions-House Receptions 1938-1940 (Box 1)
- Receptions-Senior Receptions 1881-1954 (Box 1)
- Spreads and Dinner Parties 1882-1900 (Box 1)
- Square Dances 1936 (Box 1)
- Student Teas 1887-1987 (Box 1)
- "Superdance USA" 1981 (Box 1)
- Supper Dance 1928-1946 (Box 1)